<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>~FikaMedHasse posts on ctrl-c.club</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blog.html</link><description>Blog!</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 12:23:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>PyRSS2Gen-1.1.0</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>We're on the internet babbyyyy</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/selfhosting.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Hosting this site at home now&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always been curious about selfhosting, but also kind of scared to do so. The security implications of exposing services to the world is a bit scary. Letting WAN traffic into the LAN feels a bit like leaving the door unlocked. Our ISP also gives us a dynamic IP, making DNS resolution a bit more complicated than it needs to be. But then I found out about tunnels. I had a free day to spare, and decided to finally pull the plug on this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off I bought a domain name from Cloudflare. They, nicely enough, do not charge any markup as a registrar. So I bought fikamedhasse.com for about $10. Then I flashed Debian to my SD card, booted up the Pi 4B and installed nginx. I threw up a http server serving static content on the LAN for development and testing, just mirroring the static HTML files at ctrl-c.club. Once I was satisfied I installed cloudflared on the Pi and set up a tunnel, resolving fikamedhasse.com to the Argo tunnel according to &lt;a href="https://pimylifeup.com/raspberry-pi-cloudflare-tunnel/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article. And badabing badaboom the site was public. I then installed UFW and disallowed every incoming connection except SSH from the LAN only, and disabled password login over SSH. Finally I reconfigured nginx to serve HTTPS using the origin certificate Cloudflare had been nice enough to generate, and moved the tunnel from port 80 to 443. Enabled redirect HTTP to HTTPS in the Cloudflare dashboard, and set up some cronjobs on the Pi to rsync ~/public_html from ctrl-c.club to the Pi. The synced content is not moved to the webroot, as the cronjob does not run as root. I also don't want to automatically compromise my Pi if my ctrl-c account gets compromised. Feel free to check it out and tell me what you think at &lt;a href="https://fikamedhasse.com"&gt;fikamedhasse.com&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/selfhosting.html</guid></item><item><title>nerd alert</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/hardware.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;An incomplete account of my hardware&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I aquired a PC quite late. My first tower PC, which is the same one I use today, is from 2022. Before then, I was on an old Acer Swift 5 laptop with 4GBs of RAM. It wasn't great, but computers is still a rather new hobby for me. When I started Gymnasium in 2020, at the age of 16, I got a Thinkpad X1 Yoga Carbon Gen 4 from the school for schoolwork. I knew my way around Windows thanks to an old Windows 8 Dell AIO PC we had at home, and I quickly got the hang of Windows 10, and eventually 11 as well. The Thinkpad served me alright during school, but I always knew that I wanted to put Linux on it. Windows just felt way to limiting, and I had a bit of Linux experience thanks to the Aspire, which ran Linux Mint. I used several VMs on the Thinkpad to still my need for some customizability, but the 8GBs of RAM made it a suboptimal experience. So in the second year of Gymnasium I finally decided to build a tower PC. For about 7000 SEK ($700) I bougt an MSI B550 Motherboard, Ryzen 5 5600G CPU, a 750W PSU, 16GB of RAM, an old GTX 1060 from a friend, and some other parts to make it a complete PC. I finally had something that ran Linux, and that I knew was truly mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At graduation from Gymnasium in 2023 I had the option to buy the Thinkpad for 2800 SEK (~$280), which honestly was a great deal. I bought it, flashed EndeavourOS to a flashdrive, pulled a "sudo dd if=/dev/zero of=/dev/nvme0n1 status=progress" and finally watched that Windows installation that had plagued me for so long get shredded. That laptop has since served me very well. The keyboard is fantastic, the 1440p display is crisp, and it is overall a very sexy laptop. The caveats are the soldered 8GB of RAM and the 8th gen i5 CPU. Sometime when I actually earn money I am going to get a better Thinkpad. Something with upgradeable RAM, dedicated GPU, and at least a 1440p display. Once you go HiDPI it is impossible to go back. Preferably an AMD CPU as well, since they still appear to beat Intel in power efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tower is also due an upgrade. The 1060 has done its job by now, and the 6GB of VRAM is becoming more and more apparent. Especially for AI workloads. I run ollama for LLM inferencing, and it is honestly very convenient to be able to ask questions and generate text on demand. Obviously it has a lot of shortcomings, but it is still a nice-to-have. The RTX 3090s are starting to become reasonably cheap, and the 24GB of VRAM should be a noticable upgrade. The CPU is also due an upgrade. I want to do more local compilation, but right now the linux kernel takes over an hour to compile, and I do not have that patience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, sometime in the future I want to setup a complete homelab to host my own tilde server, website, file server, *arr stack, movie collection, Jellyfin/Plex/emby/whatever server and a lot more. But that will take both time, space and money, all of which is in somewhat short supply now. It is always good to have something to look forward to as well I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/hardware.html</guid></item><item><title>Religion</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/religion.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Religion: what I think and have thunk&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is a first draft and may come to be revised in the future if I feel like it&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've always considered myself a logically oriented person. I've never really liked the more creative subjects, and have always considered maths and physics to be my best subjects in school. This, however, started shifting last year. We had religion as a subject for the first time in upper secondary, and I loved it. Religion has been part of the syllabus for as long as I've been in primary school, but it's always been "This group believes this", and never any reflection or insights into why people are religious. This led me to think of religious people as gullible, and for most of my upbringing I was a hardcore atheist. Looking back on this I cringe severely. Maybe I've grown as a person since then, but to think I used to share views with Ricky Gervais haunts me. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I still would not consider myself religious, but today I subscribe to a more "who knows" ideology. The people who subscribe to the hard empiricism and naive realism that says God isn't real just because we have yet to see proof of them seem to me a bit narrow-minded. What makes people think we can observe and notice everything around us? The view that we would notice God's existance if it was real seems to me like it overestimates humanity's perceptive abilities. If someone told a dolphin about a highly intelligent surface mammal that can trick metal into thinking for them, would the dolphin be able to tell humans from chimpanzees by observing us? Does the dolphin have the cognitive abilities to even begin to understand the question? If God is real, what makes you think you have the ability to even begin to understand their existance or its implications?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/religion.html</guid></item><item><title>Reading The Call of Cthulhu</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/cthulhu.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;The Call of Cuthulhu - the Opinions of an Unproffessional&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;i&gt;Contains spoilers for a story released like 70 years ago&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have for quite some time been reading Lovecraft on and off. One story here, another there until I reached the Call of Cuthulhu this morning. I finished it, and honestly it was somewhat underwhelming. It's undoubtedly his most famous work, but it was way more &lt;i&gt;slightly unsetteling&lt;/i&gt; than it was scary. thoroughout the entire story I was prepared for the Great Old Ones to awaken from R'lyeh and wreck havoc on civilization. But then some Norwegian man smacks into the scariest monster of all time with a boat and scares it back into the depths of the ocean. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

Of course the aspect that the old ones could return at any moment is very unsetteling, and the fact that Thurston has come to realize he is the next target of the cult and has to live in fear for the rest of his life leaves te reader rather creeped out, but reading it I expected the story to end with the end of humanity and the return of the reign of the Great Old Ones. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

The Call of Cthulhu is however not the last of Lovecraft's work featuring the Great Old Ones, so the cataclysmic event may still occur in a future novel. That begs the question, why is The Call of Cthulhu his most famous work, and not the hypothetical end-of-world story I've just made up. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

The takeaway from this is that if you want to start reading Lovecraft, The Call of Cthulhu is not the place to start. The best Lovecraft story I've read thus far is definetly The Color Out Of Space. Genuinely bone-chilling story all the way through. 10/10 Recommended, while The Call of Cthulhu gets a solid 6.5/10. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/cthulhu.html</guid></item><item><title>Reading John Green</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/alaska.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Reading &lt;i&gt;Looking for Alaska&lt;/i&gt; as someone who is probably too old to do so&lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;hr&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
     I've recently started reading &lt;i&gt;Looking for Alaska&lt;/i&gt; by John Green. It's a young adult, somewhat cheesy novel about a 16-year-olds time in a boarding school. The novel is very easy to read and a nice change to what I usually read. It feels like a breath of fresh air not having to consider any deeper meanings or analyze the themes. I always feel like there is some pressure to read these difficult, meaningful novels, but to be able to just read without thinking is sooo nice. It almost feels like I have rediscovered my love for reading. It's no longer a big undertaking to start a novel, and it takes just a couple of days of reading on my daily commute to finish the book.
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;
    I have been reading &lt;i&gt;Discworld&lt;/i&gt; by Terry Pratchett as well, and it's kinda the same thing. &lt;i&gt;Discworld&lt;/i&gt; is on a hiatus for now, but reading John Green might have inspired me to pick it back up.
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/alaska.html</guid></item><item><title>Tiling WM</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/tilingvm.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Back to using a tiling WM (for now)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm back to using a tiling WM again. I've used KDE Plasma for quite a while, but after browsing r/unixporn for a bit too much I could no longer contain the desire for ricing. So I logged back into my i3-gaps WM and got to work. Well, it wasn't exactly i3, it was actually both Plasma and i3. I had previously changed KDE's WM from kwin to i3, and had both Plasma and Plasma with i3. And let me tell you, Plasma with i3 is the perfect combination of DE and WM. You get the convenience of a DE with the speed of a WM. It's sooo sweet.&lt;br&gt;
I decided to go for a nord theme (cheesy, I know). The whole process was actually really convenient. Slap on a nice cold, blue wallpaper with nitrogen, find preconfigured .Xresources colorthemes for URxvt and a colorscheme for vim. A theme change in the browser (Vivaldi) and in Plasma took care of the rest. A complete, beautiful system in less than an hour. There are some minor things left, like a nice music visualizer (recommendations welcome) and a fetch program (recommendations also welcome) but other than that I'm really happy with the outcome.&lt;br&gt;
Writing this from my phone at work, but might post screenshots when I get home, if there is any interest in them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/tilingvm.html</guid></item><item><title>Ramblings</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/ramblings.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;A professionally incoherent text about a bit of everything&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
    I just got back from work after summer vacation. I say work, but it's really just a paid internship. School starts again in 3 weeks, and I cannot wait. This job is so boring, and I feel so unwelcome. At the same time, I do get paid, so I feel like I can't be too ungrateful. It's a big industry, and it always comes down to "Who can take care of the intern" and everyone looks down and avoids eye contact. I feel like I just get in people's way. Anyhow, It's good money for someone who hasn't really made any on their own.

    I want to go back to school, finish my education and start life for real. It feels like life is in some kind of transition state, just waiting for something real to begin. I have yet to figure out what, but I just yearn for something new, something to take me somewhere I've never been before, somewhere interesting.

    I am really excited for the future. The plan now might be software development, but for that I'd have to take higher studies, which feels like too much right now. Might also join a military education (lumpen for you Swedes). I really feel like the military could put me out of my comfort zone, and into a situation that is both uncomfortable and educational in a way that makes me appreciate what I have in a different way than I do now. Not that I consider myself ungrateful, but the things I take for granted are definetly not granted at all. I'm just incredibly lucky to have born in a high-HDI, high-GDP, developed country with good healthcare and welfare. Should probably experience some discomfort for a change.

    I don't know where I'm heading, but I'll walk with the knowledge that the road ahead will untangle sooner or later.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/ramblings.html</guid></item><item><title>Hello World!</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/HelloWorld.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Hello World!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
First blog post! How exciting. I wanted to use this opportunity to explain what this blog is, and is not:

This blog is:
    • My thoughts on whatever I feel like writing about
    • Lightweight on your browser and network
    • Simple
    • HTML + CSS only

This blog is not:
    • Professionally made
    • Professionally written
    • Professional in any other regard
    • Regularly updated
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~FikaMedHasse/blogposts/HelloWorld.html</guid></item></channel></rss>