<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>~gome posts on ctrl-c.club</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/</link><description>gome — journal</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 12:17:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>PyRSS2Gen-1.1.0</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>gome — note: 27 May 2023 — camping</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/2023-05-27.camping.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Note: going camping&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Sat, 27 May 2023 20:00:00 CDT"&gt;27 May 2023&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Hi, it’s gome, checking in with not a full post, but a note about the journal.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Since finishing my 100-post challenge, I’ve stuck to a rhythm of two posts a week.
        This coming week, though, I’ll have to forego posting, as I’ll be going on a camping trip with my dad.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;img src="img/camping.webp" width="346" height="500"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        We’re going to be backpacking (my first time).
        One night will be in a cabin, and the next two will be at backcountry sites with tents.
        We’re going to try to go sailing too, if possible.
        It should be a lot of fun.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        You can look forward to the return of regular posting here by June 6th!
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/2023-05-27.camping.html</guid></item><item><title>gome — udon</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/udon.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article class="recipe"&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Gome Udon&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Thu, 25 May 2023 22:00:00 CDT"&gt;25 May 2023, 10:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I got these good udon noodles the other day.
        A bag of them has three little serving-sized bundles in it, each wrapped in a little piece of paper.
        They’re good noodles, easy to make, and I like the portion size.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        When I was making them for the first time, I was wondering what I should put on them.
        I decided to come up with a little sauce slightly based on the ingredients from my &lt;a href="ramen.html"&gt;ramen recipe&lt;/a&gt;.
        I thought it was great, and after a couple iterations, I had measurements down for a recipe.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        One note: the udon I use says to boil it for 7 minutes and then to rinse in cold water to stop cooking.
        I like to keep them hot, so I just do 6:30 and then drain it without a rinse.
        If you want to have them cold, the sauce is still good on that too.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        As far as I know, this isn’t a traditional way to server udon or anything.
        According to Wikipedia, they’re often served in broth.
        But this sauce seems to work pretty well and the flavor is a good match, in my opinion.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;img src="img/udon.webp" width="500" height="346"&gt;
      &lt;h3 id="ingredients"&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;
      &lt;ul class="ingredient-list"&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;~2.5 oz or ~75 grams udon noodles&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1 tbsp soy sauce&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1/2 tbsp rice vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1 tsp red curry paste&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1/4 tsp garlic powder&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;1/2 tbsp avocado oil&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;h3 id="instructions"&gt;Instructions&lt;/h3&gt;
      &lt;ol&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Boil the udon as instructed on the package (mine says 7 minutes).&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;While cooking the noodles, mix all the other ingredients together in a separate container.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;After you’ve drained the noodles well, add the sauce and toss the noodles to coat them.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        If you try this recipe, send me an email and let me know what you think.
        My email is &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/udon.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — spin-up</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/spin-up.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Hobby spin-up period&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Tue, 23 May 2023 22:30:00 CDT"&gt;23 May 2023, 10:30 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        There are a lot of things I would like to learn about someday.
        There are a lot of things I wish I had started learning earlier.
        There are a lot of things I would like to learn, but probably won’t get around to in the foreseeable future, maybe ever.
        There are a lot of things I wish I had started learning, but I’m not sure if it’s worth starting now.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        When you take an interest in something, say, a new hobby, e.g. skateboarding, there’s a period of time during which you don’t really have competence in it.
        You don’t even have a full grasp of what it is you’re trying to do (you might not even know what kind of tricks are possible).
        You spend time researching and trying things out to learn what you don’t know.
        As you learn, you gain momentum in the hobby, and doing more with it (like more difficult tricks) become feasible or easier as you build your foundation.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;img src="img/skateboarding.webp" width="475" height="356"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I’ve started enough hobbies and special interests at this point to recognize this “spin-up period” as a kind of pattern.
        Usually if I’m thinking about starting something new, I’ll first pause to consider whether it’s really worth it to me to invest that spin-up period.
        This is helpful to keep me from constantly spinning my wheels on things I’m only temporarily interested in.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Unfortunately, I’m not sure the consideration is always a good thing.
        If anything, I think I tend to overestimate how long it will take me to get to a state of momentum with a new hobby.
        The overestimation probably comes from my perfectionism, which tells me that trying something new wouldn’t be worth it if it would take months to get any good at it.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I guess the important thing is to find satisfaction in every part of the process, including the learning and even the mistakes.
        Maybe the thing that got you interested in painting was seeing incredible masterpieces, and you just want to get to the part where you can do that.
        But if you can’t find interest in your first brush strokes, you’ll never get there.
        Of course, no pressure if you don’t want to do that, either!
        Basically, let’s all just try to have fun!
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Do you have things you would like to learn but don’t know if they’re worth starting?
        Does perfectionism get in the way of starting new things for you?
        In retrospect, how long was the spin-up period for one of your current hobbies?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/spin-up.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — music collection</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/music-collection.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Building my music collection&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Thu, 18 May 2023 19:30:00 CDT"&gt;18 May 2023, 7:30 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        When I wrote about &lt;a href="hours-were-the-birds.html"&gt;Hours Were the Birds&lt;/a&gt; by Adrianne Lenker, I noted how I missed the track “We Were Young”, which was removed from the re-release of the album and scrubbed from the internet.
        I had only ever listened to the song on Spotify, which is what I usually use for music listening, so when it got removed, I had no way of recovering the song I had come to love.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I was similarly disappointed when Spotify dropped Joni Mitchell: I couldn’t listen to her music on there or add it to playlists.
        In that case, at least her music wasn’t gone forever, but when 95% of your music listening is in one place, it’s hard to make a regular place for an artist within that 5%.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I have had Spotify for a long time, so I have a lot of saved albums and playlists and listening history on there that I want to keep.
        But these and many other things over the years have stacked up to make me want to eventually not have to use it.
        Maybe one day I’ll migrate everything to a different service.
        Maybe Spotify will just go out of business eventually.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;img src="img/records.webp" width="550" height="365"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        In any case, I’ve thought for a while that the best position for me to be in is to own the music I really love.
        I don’t care if it’s a digital or physical collection, as long as I have DRM-free sources for my music somewhere I can rely on.
        Right now, my plan is to buy digital audio or CDs depending on availability, and rip the CDs to a digital music library, which is probably mainly how I’ll listen for the forseeable future.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Once I have a large enough core collection, I’d like to set up some kind of media server, so I can stream my own audio to my phone remotely.
        I’d also like some way of creating and managing playlists, ideally.
        Spotify does support local music files on a per-device basis, but their support is pretty meager, and besides, I’m trying to figure out a way to not rely on Spotify.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        To buy all the albums I want would cost a lot, so I’m planning to just make it a monthly purchase for a while.
        Every month I’ll buy a couple of albums from a list of favorites I know for sure I will want in my collection.
        The list is pretty big and it keeps getting bigger over time, but if I stay consistent with growing my collection, I’ll eventually hit a critical point where I can transition to using my own collection for daily listening.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        At that point, I don’t know if I’ll stop using Spotify or keep it around so I can sample new stuff I’m interested in.
        At a certain scale, managing your own music library gets kind of difficult, and it’s even harder to outdo the convenience and features of a streaming service with your own solution.
        But at the end of the day, I don’t consider Spotify something I can rely on indefinitely, and I want a solution I know I can rely on, even if it’s imperfect.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        How do you listen to music?
        Do you have your own music collection?
        Is it difficult to manage?
        Do you know of good software for managing and streaming your own music library?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/music-collection.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — isometric</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/isometric.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;I love isometric graphics&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Tue, 16 May 2023 22:30:00 CDT"&gt;16 May 2023, 10:30 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        When I was a kid, I played Roller Coaster Tycoon (Deluxe).
        I got back into playing it a bit again in 2020, and one thing I loved about returning to it was the graphics.
        For those unfamiliar, in order to achieve a 3D-like appearance in the game without a full 3D rendering engine,
        all the graphics were prerendered in a 3D modeling program, and then in the game, those are layered graphics together to make a 3D-looking world.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        In order for this approach to work, the view can’t have any perspective, or else things would have to be different sizes depending on how far from the camera they were, and you’d be back to needing full-blown 3D.
        So instead, you use an isometric view, where everything is always the same size, or put another way, your camera doesn’t sit at a single point, but instead is equally far from everything in its view.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Roller Coaster Tycoon has a great, unique look, in part due to those techniques, but also just in general.
        You can see individual pixels, but it’s made of 3D renders, not hand-drawn pixel art.
        The whole style is covered in dithers and aliases, but for all that, it’s still remarkably legible.
        There are so many delightful little components, from the park benches &amp;amp; plants to the various buildings &amp;amp; rides.
        With all these elements packed together on the screen, you get the feeling of a diorama or little toy world, a perfect vibe for a simulator game.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;img src="img/roller_coaster_tycoon.webp" width="576" height="388"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I just love looking at these kind of graphics, and I kind of wish more games looked like this.
        One video game idea I have to add to the list of ideas I’ll probably never make is a point-and-click game with this visual style, either retelling or inspired by &lt;i&gt;The Name of the Rose&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;Il nome della rosa&lt;/i&gt;) by Umberto Eco.
        &lt;i&gt;The Name of the Rose&lt;/i&gt; is a weird postmodern mystery novel that takes place at a medieval monastery, but there’s all these misdirections and anachronisms and references to other stories in it.
        The monastery it’s set in would just be a neat setting to explore in a video game.
        And I think the kind of isometric, pre-rendered graphics RCT uses could give it a displaced-in-time feeling that would fit very well with its postmodern themes.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Have you played Roller Coaster Tycoon or RCT 2?
        What do you think of its graphics?
        Have you read &lt;i&gt;The Name of the Rose&lt;/i&gt;?
        Do you think it would make a good video game?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/isometric.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — ratioscore</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/ratioscore.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;I just learned about Ratioscore&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Thu, 11 May 2023 18:00:00 CDT"&gt;11 May 2023, 6:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        For a while now, I’ve wanted to use my programming skills and my knowledge of just intonation to build a useful tool for those interested in learning or writing in just intonation.
        My ideas include:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;a JI piano roll, where clicking on a note shows you its relation to every other note&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;a matching game where you learn to construct rational intervals with a drag &amp;amp; drop interface&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;a programming language for notating just intonation scores, which could then generate sheet music or audio/MIDI&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Until a few days ago, I was unaware of any tools that did these things.
        But I happened upon &lt;a href="https://ratioscore.humdrum.org/"&gt;Ratioscore&lt;/a&gt;, and it does a lot of the same things I wanted to do with the programming language idea.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/electric_piano.webp" width="450" height="338"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Yamaha_CP-70M_ready_to_play.jpg#Licensing" target="_blank"&gt;Michael Müller-Hillebrand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I’ve wanted to get more into just intonation before, but I had limited tools, and I found it prohibitively difficult to produce JI audio.
        With something like Ratioscore in my toolkit, I’ll be able to learn &amp;amp; experiment more, and practice writing my own music in just intonation.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Ratioscore will be useful for now, but I still haven’t given up on making my own just intonation tools.
        I think with the right interface, JI could be made a lot more intuitive to the uninitiated.
        I might even still try to make my own version of a JI language, because I’d like some fancier features than what Ratioscore offers.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Here’s a passage from &lt;a href=".."&gt;gomepage anthem&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;Orchard Glen&lt;/i&gt; I produced in Ratioscore.
        It’s mostly 5-limit, with just a little bit of 7 thrown in on one chord.
        I felt like doing it brushed off my old skills and taught me some new things, and I’m looking forward to doing more.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="music-box"&gt;
        &lt;audio src="img/orchard_glen_JI_1.mp3"&gt;&lt;/audio&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="play"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="pause"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;span&gt;Orchard Glen, just intonation&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class="music-box"&gt;
        &lt;audio src="img/orchard_glen_JI_2.mp3"&gt;&lt;/audio&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="play"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="pause"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;span&gt;Orchard Glen, just intonation, zippy version&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Have you used Ratioscore?
        Do you know of other useful just intonation tools?
        What do you think of the JI version of Orchard Glen?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/ratioscore.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — health</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/health.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Basic health stack&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Tue, 9 May 2023 23:00:00 CDT"&gt;9 May 2023, 11:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        In programming, a set of interacting components in a software architecture is sometimes called a “stack”.
        I’ve seen people online use the word to point at a more general version of the same idea.
        Like a lot of exported software terms, it has kind of a goofy connotation to me, like people are trying to turn our whole conceptual space into cool techy-sounding jargon or something.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        On the other hand, “basic health stack” does seem to work well to describe the idea I have in mind today.
        I try to keep healthy habits, but I struggle to keep them all going all the time.
        It seems like sometimes I just have to let them go for a bit, and then pick them back up when I’m able.
        The same goes for refraining for bad habits.
        Sometimes I’ll fall back into them for a bit, but I think it’s okay as long as I can break them again later.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/sepak_takraw.webp" width="500" height="375"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href="http://www.korea.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Korea.net&lt;/a&gt; / Korean Culture and Information Service (Jeon Han)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The tricky part is, these habits build on each other in both directions.
        When I feel good, I have an easier time doing the things that make me feel good.
        When I feel bad, I let more healthy habits go, and it creates a vicious cycle.
        So if I want to continue to feel good, I want my lapses to be somewhat strategic, so I don’t lose a good cycle or start a bad one.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        With all that in mind, I’ve tried to figure out the core set of things I need to do most of the time in order to feel well, that is, my “basic health stack”.
        Ideally, these would be the last habits I drop, if I need to drop some habits.
        Not all of them need to be adhered to daily, but the longer I go without them, the more I risk a vicious cycle.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        The list I’ve come up with so far:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;sleep; eight hours a night, with bedtime ideally before 10:30 PM (as I publish this at 11:00 PM, haha)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;healthy eating; for me this is basically less sugar &amp;amp; carbs, and then trying to eat whatever I feel like my body is asking for&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;exercise; aerobic workouts like running &amp;amp; biking make me feel especially good, but if I lift weights with good focus that seems to be just as beneficial&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;new experiences; I find that getting outside my comfort zone regularly is necessary or else I start to get locked into a single perspective or lose my confidence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        One more thing I’m considering for the list is something like “committments” or “obligations”.
        I’m not sure exactly what to call it, but I think it’s important to be needed for things that are bigger than just yourself, that you’re not doing for just yourself.
        Being in a relatively uncommitted stage of life, I sometimes need to seek these things out more intentionally.
        They keep me out of just my own little world, and they help me grow as a person.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Do you have a “basic health stack”?
        Are the things I listed important for you?
        Are there any items I’m missing you think most people would need in their stack?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/health.html</guid></item></channel></rss>