<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>~gome posts on ctrl-c.club</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/</link><description>gome — journal</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 00:48:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>PyRSS2Gen-1.1.0</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>gome — ratioscore</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/ratioscore.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;I just learned about Ratioscore&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Thu, 11 May 2023 18:00:00 CDT"&gt;11 May 2023, 6:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        For a while now, I’ve wanted to use my programming skills and my knowledge of just intonation to build a useful tool for those interested in learning or writing in just intonation.
        My ideas include:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;a JI piano roll, where clicking on a note shows you its relation to every other note&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;a matching game where you learn to construct rational intervals with a drag &amp;amp; drop interface&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;a programming language for notating just intonation scores, which could then generate sheet music or audio/MIDI&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Until a few days ago, I was unaware of any tools that did these things.
        But I happened upon &lt;a href="https://ratioscore.humdrum.org/"&gt;Ratioscore&lt;/a&gt;, and it does a lot of the same things I wanted to do with the programming language idea.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/electric_piano.webp" width="450" height="338"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Yamaha_CP-70M_ready_to_play.jpg#Licensing" target="_blank"&gt;Michael Müller-Hillebrand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I’ve wanted to get more into just intonation before, but I had limited tools, and I found it prohibitively difficult to produce JI audio.
        With something like Ratioscore in my toolkit, I’ll be able to learn &amp;amp; experiment more, and practice writing my own music in just intonation.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Ratioscore will be useful for now, but I still haven’t given up on making my own just intonation tools.
        I think with the right interface, JI could be made a lot more intuitive to the uninitiated.
        I might even still try to make my own version of a JI language, because I’d like some fancier features than what Ratioscore offers.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Here’s a passage from &lt;a href=".."&gt;gomepage anthem&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;Orchard Glen&lt;/i&gt; I produced in Ratioscore.
        It’s mostly 5-limit, with just a little bit of 7 thrown in on one chord.
        I felt like doing it brushed off my old skills and taught me some new things, and I’m looking forward to doing more.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;div class="music-box"&gt;
        &lt;audio src="img/orchard_glen_JI_1.mp3"&gt;&lt;/audio&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="play"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="pause"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;span&gt;Orchard Glen, just intonation&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;div class="music-box"&gt;
        &lt;audio src="img/orchard_glen_JI_2.mp3"&gt;&lt;/audio&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="play"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;svg width="20" height="20" class="pause"&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;span&gt;Orchard Glen, just intonation, zippy version&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Have you used Ratioscore?
        Do you know of other useful just intonation tools?
        What do you think of the JI version of Orchard Glen?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/ratioscore.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — health</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/health.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Basic health stack&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Tue, 9 May 2023 23:00:00 CDT"&gt;9 May 2023, 11:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        In programming, a set of interacting components in a software architecture is sometimes called a “stack”.
        I’ve seen people online use the word to point at a more general version of the same idea.
        Like a lot of exported software terms, it has kind of a goofy connotation to me, like people are trying to turn our whole conceptual space into cool techy-sounding jargon or something.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        On the other hand, “basic health stack” does seem to work well to describe the idea I have in mind today.
        I try to keep healthy habits, but I struggle to keep them all going all the time.
        It seems like sometimes I just have to let them go for a bit, and then pick them back up when I’m able.
        The same goes for refraining for bad habits.
        Sometimes I’ll fall back into them for a bit, but I think it’s okay as long as I can break them again later.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/sepak_takraw.webp" width="500" height="375"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href="http://www.korea.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Korea.net&lt;/a&gt; / Korean Culture and Information Service (Jeon Han)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The tricky part is, these habits build on each other in both directions.
        When I feel good, I have an easier time doing the things that make me feel good.
        When I feel bad, I let more healthy habits go, and it creates a vicious cycle.
        So if I want to continue to feel good, I want my lapses to be somewhat strategic, so I don’t lose a good cycle or start a bad one.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        With all that in mind, I’ve tried to figure out the core set of things I need to do most of the time in order to feel well, that is, my “basic health stack”.
        Ideally, these would be the last habits I drop, if I need to drop some habits.
        Not all of them need to be adhered to daily, but the longer I go without them, the more I risk a vicious cycle.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        The list I’ve come up with so far:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;sleep; eight hours a night, with bedtime ideally before 10:30 PM (as I publish this at 11:00 PM, haha)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;healthy eating; for me this is basically less sugar &amp;amp; carbs, and then trying to eat whatever I feel like my body is asking for&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;exercise; aerobic workouts like running &amp;amp; biking make me feel especially good, but if I lift weights with good focus that seems to be just as beneficial&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;new experiences; I find that getting outside my comfort zone regularly is necessary or else I start to get locked into a single perspective or lose my confidence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        One more thing I’m considering for the list is something like “committments” or “obligations”.
        I’m not sure exactly what to call it, but I think it’s important to be needed for things that are bigger than just yourself, that you’re not doing for just yourself.
        Being in a relatively uncommitted stage of life, I sometimes need to seek these things out more intentionally.
        They keep me out of just my own little world, and they help me grow as a person.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Do you have a “basic health stack”?
        Are the things I listed important for you?
        Are there any items I’m missing you think most people would need in their stack?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/health.html</guid></item></channel></rss>