<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>~gome posts on ctrl-c.club</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/</link><description>gome — journal</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 06:13:29 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>PyRSS2Gen-1.1.0</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>gome — health</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/health.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Basic health stack&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Tue, 9 May 2023 23:00:00 CDT"&gt;9 May 2023, 11:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        In programming, a set of interacting components in a software architecture is sometimes called a “stack”.
        I’ve seen people online use the word to point at a more general version of the same idea.
        Like a lot of exported software terms, it has kind of a goofy connotation to me, like people are trying to turn our whole conceptual space into cool techy-sounding jargon or something.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        On the other hand, “basic health stack” does seem to work well to describe the idea I have in mind today.
        I try to keep healthy habits, but I struggle to keep them all going all the time.
        It seems like sometimes I just have to let them go for a bit, and then pick them back up when I’m able.
        The same goes for refraining for bad habits.
        Sometimes I’ll fall back into them for a bit, but I think it’s okay as long as I can break them again later.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/sepak_takraw.webp" width="500" height="375"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href="http://www.korea.net/" target="_blank"&gt;Korea.net&lt;/a&gt; / Korean Culture and Information Service (Jeon Han)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        The tricky part is, these habits build on each other in both directions.
        When I feel good, I have an easier time doing the things that make me feel good.
        When I feel bad, I let more healthy habits go, and it creates a vicious cycle.
        So if I want to continue to feel good, I want my lapses to be somewhat strategic, so I don’t lose a good cycle or start a bad one.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        With all that in mind, I’ve tried to figure out the core set of things I need to do most of the time in order to feel well, that is, my “basic health stack”.
        Ideally, these would be the last habits I drop, if I need to drop some habits.
        Not all of them need to be adhered to daily, but the longer I go without them, the more I risk a vicious cycle.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        The list I’ve come up with so far:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;sleep; eight hours a night, with bedtime ideally before 10:30 PM (as I publish this at 11:00 PM, haha)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;healthy eating; for me this is basically less sugar &amp;amp; carbs, and then trying to eat whatever I feel like my body is asking for&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;exercise; aerobic workouts like running &amp;amp; biking make me feel especially good, but if I lift weights with good focus that seems to be just as beneficial&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;new experiences; I find that getting outside my comfort zone regularly is necessary or else I start to get locked into a single perspective or lose my confidence&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        One more thing I’m considering for the list is something like “committments” or “obligations”.
        I’m not sure exactly what to call it, but I think it’s important to be needed for things that are bigger than just yourself, that you’re not doing for just yourself.
        Being in a relatively uncommitted stage of life, I sometimes need to seek these things out more intentionally.
        They keep me out of just my own little world, and they help me grow as a person.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Do you have a “basic health stack”?
        Are the things I listed important for you?
        Are there any items I’m missing you think most people would need in their stack?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/health.html</guid></item></channel></rss>