<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>~gome posts on ctrl-c.club</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/</link><description>gome — journal</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 06:13:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>PyRSS2Gen-1.1.0</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>gome — writing</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/dowsing.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;What’s up with dowsing?&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Tue, 2 May 2023 22:00:00 CDT"&gt;2 May 2023, 10:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Today at dinner my dad was talking about a podcast he had heard where they talked about dowsing.
        For the unfamiliar, dowsing is a technique used to find hidden things, such as underground water or gravesites.
        The dowser often uses a rod or pair of rods, which are meant to guide them toward whatever it is they’re looking for.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        The episode my dad listened to gave some impressive anectdotal examples of dowsing being used to find things.
        Obviously these are only examples, and if this were all I had heard, I wouldn’t be that interested.
        But I actually have a personal connection to the practice in my family history.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I’ve heard a few times from my mom that my grandfather actually had a pair of dowsing rods, and used them with some success.
        To be clear, my grandpa wasn’t some paranormal enthusiast or pseudoscience quack.
        He was a farmer of the American heartland, and not prone to eccentricity or superstition.
        He did dowsing because it produced practical results for him.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;img src="img/dowser.webp" width="490" height="480"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I don’t really have a clear picture of his success rate with it, but I do know that he used his rods to find water and the graves of relatives.
        And it must have worked well enough for him that he did it regularly; it’s not like he tried it once &amp;amp; gave up.
        My understanding is that it’s not uncommon for old farmers to have some experience with dowsing, especially for finding water.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        So, what exactly is going on with dowsing?
        I don’t think anyone really knows, but I have a general theory I’ve picked up about things like this.
        People receive a lot of sensory information that never makes it to their conscious mind, but still gets processed.
        Some of this sensory information might be conditions in the feel of the ground or the air that give an experienced mind clues to where water might be.
        Processes like dowsing might give the unconscious a way to pass that information along to the conscious mind, bypassing the layer of filtering that would normally interfere with that intuition.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        As I said, it’s just a general theory.
        Practices like dowsing are still mostly a mystery.
        But the interesting thing about it is that you can have no clue how it works, and it might still work for you.
        And if it works, why not use it?
        There seems to be some variation among people in their aptitude for it, but I’d like to give it a try sometime and see for myself.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Have you ever heard stories of dowsing working?
        Have you ever tried dowsing?
        Do you think there’s anything to the theory I gave?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/dowsing.html</guid></item><item><title>gome — writing</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/writing.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;I miss writing every day&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Thu, 27 Apr 2023 21:30:00 CDT"&gt;27 Apr 2023, 9:30 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        When I &lt;a href="incorrect.html"&gt;finished&lt;/a&gt; my 100-day writing challenge, I made a point of stopping the daily writing.
        I had developed the habit so well by that point that it would have been easy to continue,
        but I wanted there to be a cutoff that clearly delineated the challenge in my mind.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        One of the reasons I was able to commit to the challenge in the first place was that I knew it was a limited scope.
        It wasn’t like I was committing to daily writing “forever”, which I probably would have failed at much sooner.
        So I wanted to honor that limited scope by not carrying on indefinitely with it.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I want to keep writing, but at the same time, I think it will be more difficult now that I’m not doing it daily.
        I decided to commit to two posts a week for now, because I knew if I made no commitments, I would probably let other things get in the way and never finish another post.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/stove.webp" width="550" height="309"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:GasStoveBurner_20220521_181829.jpg#Licensing" target="_blank"&gt;Ka23 13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        When I did posts daily, it was just a part of my regular routine to get it done.
        Even if I didn’t feel like writing, I knew on some level that I would have to sit down and work it out until I had a post.
        Now that I have more space between the posts, it feels like more time is required to get me back into the mindset.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I think there’s a big psychological difference between something you do daily and things you do regularly but less frequently, especially in creative activities.
        When you do something daily, you keep it “warm”.
        Every time you sit down to do it, the last time is close in your memory, so you can draw from the prior feeling of momentum more easily.
        It creates a sense of flow between days you don’t get if you let the activity go cold, even for a single day.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I’ve actually noticed the same thing writing music.
        I can really only get good ideas for music after thinking about it for a few consecutive days,
        and I usually do my best work once I’ve sat down and worked at the piano for a few days in a row.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I still have a lot of thoughts in my head I would like to share.
        Daily posting might make it easier to get more of them out.
        But the only way I’ll write daily posts is if I commit to daily posting beforehand, because otherwise I will end up doing other things most days.
        So perhaps I’ll come up with another posting schedule that is more intermittent but lets me reap the benefits of daily posting again.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Have you ever written daily posts?
        Did you stop intentionally at some point?
        Do you find that the things you do daily stay warm in your mind?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/writing.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — git</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/git.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;You don’t need GitHub&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Mon, 24 Apr 2023 23:00:00 CDT"&gt;24 Apr 2023, 11:00 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        Like most programmers, I use git for version control.
        I’ve been using it since college, where we were introduced to it for working on shared projects as well as a consistent way to turn our code in.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        There were a lot of things I didn’t get about git when I first started using it.
        If I needed to do anything besides simply add commits to a single branch in a linear fashion and push them to a remote, I got confused quickly.
        I would try to consult a guide or StackOverflow post, typing in commands I didn’t understand and usually I made a mess of things.
        I remember I would end up force-pushing to remote a lot, which I understood was a no-no, but at the time, the repositories I was working with were mine alone, so it didn’t really matter.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Now that I’ve used it for work and actually had to contend with things like stashes and branches and remotes over &amp;amp; over again, I feel like I’ve got a more stable handle on git than I used to.
        At the very least, I can do what I need to for work pretty reliably, and I know how to get myself out of the sticky spots well enough.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;img src="img/network.webp" width="355" height="352" class="no-border"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        There’s one really interesting thing about git I didn’t understand until recently.
        When you push to a remote repository, such as those hosted on GitHub, there’s really nothing privileged about it compared to any other repository.
        The only difference is that it’s what’s called a “bare” repository, which means it doesn’t actually keep a working tree (the instantiation of a repo’s files on a given filesystem).
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        The upshot of this is that you can actually push &amp;amp; pull repositories from any machine you can SSH to that has git installed.
        So you don’t need to use a separate hosting service to store your code, especially if you’re mainly pushing it to pull it down onto another machine you have access to.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        For example, I use git to &lt;a href="update.html"&gt;deploy my website&lt;/a&gt;.
        When I wrote that post, I would always push my repository to tildegit, then log into the Ctrl-C server and pull it back down.
        Since learning this little tidbit, I ended up reworking my setup so that when I do a &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;, it actually goes to tildegit &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; the ctrl-c server directly, so no additional pulling is necessary.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        To make this work, I had to do two things.
        The first was to add an additional url to the &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; remote:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;
        git remote set-url --add --push origin ctrl-c:public_html
      &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        If you use this command, replace &lt;code&gt;ctrl-c:public_html&lt;/code&gt; with your own hostname and repo path.
        In my case, I have the &lt;code&gt;ctrl-c&lt;/code&gt; hostname configured to connect to the Ctrl-C server in my &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; file,
        and &lt;code&gt;public_html&lt;/code&gt; is the directory the actual repository resides in, relative to my home directory on the Ctrl-C server.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        The second thing was to update the config of the repository on the Ctrl-C server:
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;
        git config receive.denycurrentbranch updateInstead
      &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Above, I mentioned that remote repositories on hosting services are “bare”, that is, they have no working tree.
        If you have a normal repository with a working tree, and you push an update to the branch it currently has checked out, it would normally deny your update.
        When you set this setting, it will update the repository instead.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        If you use this approach to deploy websites or other files, it’s best to avoid making changes in the remote repository if you can.
        Also, there are more sophisticated ways to do this kind of thing, so don’t take this as expert advice.
        But at the very least, it’s a cool trick that suits my needs for deploying a personal site quite well.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Do you use git?
        Do you feel like you grasp it pretty well?
        Have you ever discovered a neat trick that helps your workflow?
        Have you tried managing git repositories in a similar way before?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/git.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — incorrect</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/incorrect.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Giving myself permission to be confidently incorrect&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Wed, 19 Apr 2023 19:30:00 CDT"&gt;19 Apr 2023, 7:30 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;div class="note"&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
          This is my 100&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; post for the &lt;a href="https://jibran.substack.com/p/100-day-creator-challenge"&gt;100-day writing challenge&lt;/a&gt; I’ve been participating in.
          As of publication, I have completed the challenge: publishing, without exception, at least 100 words every day for 100 weekdays.
          When I started, I never really thought I would ever complete 100 of something so consistently, but here I am.
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
          If you’ve been reading, thanks for following along on this journey.
          Big thanks to Jibran el Bazi for putting this challenge on!
          Thanks as well to everyone who participated; it’s been so much fun writing alongside you, and your daily posts kept me motivated to stay committed to my own.
        &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
          I will continue to publish regularly, but for the next while, I’m going to go down to two posts a week.
          Daily posting is a big time commitment, and I’d like to put some of that time towards building out other parts of my gomesite, as well as some offline pursuits, especially since it’s &lt;a href="spring.html"&gt;finally warming up here&lt;/a&gt;.
        &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        My little sister just told me how one time, in school, a kid in her class was just talking and kind of unthinkingly said something he probably shouldn’t have.
        In response, the teacher said something like, “wow, that really tells me a lot about what kind of person you are.”
        I understand the impulse to try to get the kid to think about what he says, but what a terrible way to do it!
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Treating minor mistakes as deep reflections of a kid’s character is not a healthy lesson to teach.
        It teaches them that their mistakes are a reflection of a bad essential nature.
        It teaches them that they need to watch everything they say, lest they accidentally reveal themselves to be a stupid or bad person.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I think I was similar to this kid in some ways when I was younger.
        I’ve always loved to talk a lot and I still do.
        As a kid, this lead me to regularly say some pretty stupid, wrong, and bad things.
        At some point, I think I became deeply embarassed of saying wrong things, and tried really hard to avoid it all the time.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/tomatoes.webp" width="550" height="309"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo credit: &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:20160528_Whitstable_-_Solanum_lycopersicum_1.jpg#Licensing" target="_blank"&gt;Emőke Dénes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        When you need to avoid being wrong, but you also want to talk all the time, you end up becoming very pedantic.
        I obsess over endless levels of nuance with almost any idea I have, because I hate the feeling of telling someone something I think and having them poke holes in it easily.
        In some cases, I’m probably more interested in having ideas that are difficult to refute (i.e., correct-sounding ones) than useful or accurate ones.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        The defensive level of nuance is especially present in my writing, which I was trained through school to approach adversarially.
        Whatever claim you make, think about what a devil’s advocate would say.
        I’m good at seeking out that extra layer of nuance, so wouldn’t I be remiss if I didn’t include it?
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I’ve &lt;a href="funny.html"&gt;written before&lt;/a&gt; about how I show less of my personality in my writing than I’d like.
        The biggest reason is probably because I get sidetracked with correctness, rather than being true to what I want to say.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        This writing challenge has already been a huge help in unblocking ideas that I wanted to talk about, but was hesitant to put into words.
        Going forward, I’d like to do a better job of feeling free to say things as I really think or feel them at a given moment in time, even if they’re somewhat “wrong” by some standard or another.
        Perhaps people will correct me with things I was already aware of; isn’t that something I can survive?
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Not everything needs to be defended with the maximum level of nuance.
        Some ideas will only ever be refined if we expose them to the criticism of others.
        Other ideas, strong and beautiful ones at that, can only ever be expressed through an imperfect vessel of imperfect words.
        Even something “wrong” can be used to express the truth.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Do you feel like you can be wrong?
        Have you been pedantic or defensively nuanced?
        Do you sometimes have to say the wrong thing before you can say the right thing?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/incorrect.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — spring</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/spring.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;The spring melt&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Tue, 18 Apr 2023 22:30:00 CDT"&gt;18 Apr 2023, 10:30 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        A consistent theme in my writing on here has been the winter I’ve been living through, the span of which coincided closely with the 100-day writing challenge I’m doing.
        I felt a distinct change in the feel of the season about a month ago, close to when the equinox actually occurred.
        We were still covered in snow, and would continue to get snow for a couple more weeks, but the days were getting longer and brighter, and along with the shift to daylight time, the feeling of spring was already on the way.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Now we’ve actually reached the point where the temperatures are finally overtaking the big backlog of snow to melt.
        With all the melt draining away, I’m hoping to go see the river sometime near its crest.
        Everything’s super wet right now, but it’s already getting easier, little by little, to get outside and do things.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        As it gets warmer, my favorite thing is to notice the memories of past springs that come back.
        They’re activated by the particular feeling of the air on a given day, or by smells that get easier to detect in warmer air, especially that of water-logged earth.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/charles_beck_spring_flight.webp" width="654" height="442"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;
          &lt;i&gt;Spring Flight&lt;/i&gt; by Charles Beck (&lt;a href="https://kaddatz-galleries.square.site/product/charles-beck-spring-flight-15-150/2548" target="_blank"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        During winter, with these physical memories unavailable, there are certain thoughts you just can’t think, until the spring comes and gently unblocks them.
        I think of the process as an “inner melt” that accompanies the exterior one.
        It’s a helpful reminder that you’re not always a unitary “complete self”, necessarily, but that there are aspects of your personality that move and flow with the seasons.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Winter is almost always something of an emotional battle in this climate.
        But I really do think it makes the arrival of spring feel that much more meaningful.
        I can’t imagine living somewhere where the seasons don’t really have distinct shapes, as pleasant as that might be.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        What is the weather like where you live?
        When did the spring start for you?
        Do you notice memories or internal changes that follow with the seasons?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/geese.webp" width="550" height="367"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;
          Bonus image: Basically &lt;i&gt;Spring Flight&lt;/i&gt; but in real life!
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/spring.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>gome — website</title><link>https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/website.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;article&gt;
      &lt;h1 id="title"&gt;Build your own website&lt;/h1&gt;
      &lt;time datetime="Mon, 17 Apr 2023 23:30:00 CDT"&gt;17 Apr 2023, 11:30 PM&lt;/time&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        I was going to start this post by talking about social media, but I think most of us are pretty well aware of the ways social media sucks.
        I follow some social media, but I don’t really post much on large sites.
        There’s stuff I would like to share online (hence this blog), but social media feels alienating and vaguely threatening to me.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        In contrast, having my own website has been a joy.
        Building this website and participating on Ctrl-C Club has been a real experience of the magic of the internet for me.
        It’s so much fun to share things on my site and hear back from readers about their thoughts.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        I also love having full creative control over my web presence here.
        There’s no social media site where I’d be able to have a profile page that looks like &lt;a href="/"&gt;my gomepage&lt;/a&gt;.
        And no matter how customizable they get, those sites are (of necessity) restricted to specific structures and formats: you can only post videos on YouTube; you can only post tweets on Twitter.*
        With your own website, the only limits are your imagination and your skills.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;figure&gt;
        &lt;img src="img/nightdrift.webp" width="660" height="444"&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;
          &lt;a href="https://nightdrift.neocities.org/"&gt;Nightdrifter’s Lounge&lt;/a&gt; is just one example of the creative and awesome-looking sites people make on Neocities.
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
      &lt;/figure&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;
        There’s a higher barrier to entry when making your own website, because it requires you to learn HTML at a bare minimum, probably CSS as well, and eventually, you might want to add Javascript or even server-side code to it.
        But it’s not hard to grasp the barest basics to get a site started, and once you have a start, you can learn as you go.
        A site can be updated any time, so your site grows and improves over time as a reflection of your own journey of learning.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        You don’t have to pay anything to start a website, either.
        Gomepage started on &lt;a href="https://ctrl-c.club/"&gt;Ctrl-C Club&lt;/a&gt;, which gives out free user profiles on a shared Linux machine, which include a &lt;code&gt;public_html&lt;/code&gt; directory you can use to publish a user page.
        There are a &lt;a href="https://tildeverse.org/members/"&gt;number of “tilde” servers&lt;/a&gt; that offer similar things.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        If you don’t want to log in through a command line, there are other ways to host a static site for free.
        &lt;a href="https://neocities.org/"&gt;Neocities&lt;/a&gt; is a great site, inspired by the classic web host GeoCities.
        This is probably one of the easiest ways out there to get your own website.
        I love browsing around and seeing the fun, often retro sites people are building on there.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        If you are familiar with git, the version control software, &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pages.cloudflare.com/"&gt;Cloudflare Pages&lt;/a&gt; both let you deploy a site automatically from files in a git repository, which is convenient.
        I’m sure there are plenty of other free options for hosting out there, but these are just the ones that come to me from memory.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Home-made personal websites take more time, effort, and attention than social media, and so they will likely never be as popular.
        But it means they draw a more intentional and engaged community of authors and users.
        No matter what the majority is doing, fun &amp;amp; interesting alternatives are out there, waiting for us.
        In the same way &lt;a href="regenerative.html"&gt;regenerative agriculture&lt;/a&gt; eschews raw efficiency for ecological resilience and diversity, having your own website is like building a digital homestead (or be as it may, a “gomestead”) that supports a healthier online ecosystem.
        Come join us!
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
        Do you have a currently active personal site?
        Have you tried making a website before?
        Do you want to try making one?
        Let me know your thoughts at my Ctrl-C email: &lt;code&gt;gome&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;@&lt;span&gt; ​&lt;/span&gt;ctrl-c.club&lt;/code&gt;.
      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p class="footnote"&gt;
        * I know neither of these are perfect examples. On YouTube, you can now also make community posts, and Twitter in particular does allow some rudimentary forms of user-created structure with threading and quote-tweeting. But in either case, the format of the content will always be restricted to what features those sites have created.
      &lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/article&gt;
  
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ctrl-c.club/~gome/journal/website.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>